Guide to the Paul Goodman collection, circa 1934-1987
Goodman, Paul collection,
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Paul Goodman collection, circa 1934-1987
8063
Paul Goodman, 1911-1972
3.1 cubic feet
Manuscripts, letters, proofs, galley proofs, ephemera, books, periodicals, programs, sheet music, manuscript scores, 1 watercolor plan.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Manuscripts and publications by and about Paul Goodman and his fields of interest.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
American sociologist, poet, fiction writer, social critic, activist, and public intellectual, author of many publications including his book Growing up absurd: problems of youth in the organized system (1960). Goodman wrote on the American educational system, psychology, architecture, homosexuality and gay rights, and political issues including the New Left, the Vietnam War, anarchism, and pacifism, among other subjects.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Page proofs and galley proofs of Goodman's book Speaking and language: defence of poetry, with inserts by the author; galley proofs of his Collected poems; proofs of his book New reformation; typescript of his play Faustina, with his corrections in pencil; letters from him to his friend Arnold Canell; program from his memorial service; periodicals containing articles by or about Goodman; ephemera such as flyers, theater programs, and pamphlets; manuscript scores of three songs with words by Goodman and music by Ned Rorem; and sound recordings by Goodman or based on his writings. Also, a draft of Tom Nicely's Paul Goodman bibliography, Adam and his work, with related correspondence and reviews (1973-1980). Also, a watercolor plan of Manhattan by Paul Goodman and his brother Percival, including a "business and industry" area down the middle of Manhattan island (where Central Park now is), surrounded by "residences in parks." This plan was probably created in connection with the Federal Writers Project, circa 1936-1938. Correspondents in the collection include Burton Weiss, Eliot Glassheim, Robert Merideth, and Tom Nicely.
Published items cataloged individually include books and other separately published works, offprints, art exhibition catalogues with text by Goodman, sheet music, LP records, and additional periodical articles by or about Goodman.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Goodman, Paul, 1911-1972.; Goodman, Paul, 1911-1972.; Nicely, Tom, 1939- Adam and his work.; Canell, Arnold.; Nicely, Tom, 1939-; Weiss, Burton I.; Glassheim, Eliot, 1938-; Merideth, Robert.; Goodman, Percival.; Rorem, Ned, 1923-; Nicely, Tom, 1939- Adam and his work.; Federal Writers' Project.
Subjects:
United States--Social conditions--20th century.; United States--Politics and government--20th century.; City planning--New York (State)--New York.
Form and Genre Terms:
Galley proofs.; Page proofs.; Plans (maps); Scores (documents for music)
INFORMATION FOR USERS
Item inventory by donor.
CONTAINER LIST
- Galley proofs and page proofs of Speaking and Language: Defence of Poetry, with long inserts by the author (Box 1)
- Galley proofs of New Reformation (Box 2)
- Collected Poems: final typescript; setting copy (Box 3)
- Collected Poems: galley proofs; page proofs (Box 4)
- Collected Poems: page proofs; blue-line proofs; papers and letters from Taylor Stoehr's files; mock-up of title page and sample page layouts; papers and letters from Sally Goodman's files (Box 5)
- Letters from Paul Goodman to Arnold Canell, 1929-1943 (Box 6)
- Typescript of Faustina; Mexican periodical Plural, November 1971, containing article by Goodman; offprints; program for Goodman's memorial service, pamphlets, flyers, and other ephemera (Box 7)
- Periodical articles by or about Goodman; his poem "Two Sentences"; Iain Sinclair, The Kodak Mantra Diaries (Box 8)
- Draft of Tom Nicely's Paul Goodman bibliography Adam and his work, with related correspondence and reviews, 1973-1980 (Box 9)
- "Manhattan" (Watercolor plan), by Percival and Paul Goodman, circa 1936-1938 (Mapcase folder 1)
- Manuscript piano-vocal scores of songs by Ned Rorem, words by Paul Goodman: "Poem"; "Bawling Blues" (notated "Jefferson Diner, 3:00 am"); "Absalom", undated (1940s?); The song "Poem" was published as "The lordly Hudson" in 1947. (Mapcase folder 2)